Mss.B.L23m
American Philosophical Society
Biographical data on Karl Landsteiner, 1923-1952
Mss.B.L23m
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet 650 items
Correspondence of Dr. George M. Mackenzie with friends and associates of Karl Landsteiner; memoranda of conversations; notes and recollections of Landsteiner by Thomas M. Rivers, 1944-1952, and by Max Neuberger; Landsteiner's departmental reports at Rockefeller Institute, 1923-1943; correspondence on publications. There is much material on immunology, the study of blood, the Nobel award, 1930, antisemitism, and the Vienna medical schools.
650 items.
Mackenzie, George M.,collector.
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by the Landsteiner family and accessioned, 1958 (1958 1622ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Karl Landsteiner was a medical researcher and Nobel laureate. He was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1935.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
When Karl Landsteiner left Vienna in 1922 at the age of fifty-four to join the Rockefeller Institute, he had already done much of his most important work. In the early years of the century he had discovered a simple technique of agglutination, whereby human blood was divided into four groups, a discovery that made possible safe blood transfusions. This work, in turn, led him to the study of hereditary differences in antigens of blood groups, and thus to the birth of serological genetics. A succession of discoveries followed in the 1920s and 1930s, after he had moved to the Rockefeller Institute: the discovery of blood factors (M, N, P, and Rh factors), and investigations on the chemical specificity of serological reactions, which became a basis of immunochemistry. Landsteiner was awarded the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1930.
After Landsteiner's death, George M. Mackenzie began collecting materials for a biography: correspondence with friends and associates of Landsteiner, memoranda of conversations, notes and recollections of Landsteiner by Thomas M. Rivers (1944-1952) and by Max Neuberger, annual reports from Landsteiner's laboratory at the Institute (1923-1943), correspondence on publications and the Nobel Prize, and raw material on immunology and the study of blood. These materials comprise the Landsteiner Collection (the biography was never completed). Of special interest are records on medical education in Vienna, the growth of anti-Semitism, and correspondence with Simon Flexner which led to Landsteiner's move to the Institute.
The collection is eclectic and contains large gaps (many scribbled notes), but it is useful as a supplemental background source on Landsteiner. The collection is complemented by the Landsteiner correspondence in the Simon Flexner Papers (B F365), which contains administrative and scientific material on Landsteiner's laboratory. There is also substantial material on Landsteiner in the Peyton Rous Papers (B R77).
Mackenzie, George M. Anti-Semitism ( For use in the biography of Karl Landsteiner. Includes "The Founder of Political Anti-Semitism: Georg von Schoenerer" by Oscar Karbach (1945).) Correspondence (120 pages) 1945, 1948, n.d. English
Mackenzie, George M. Memorandum of conversation with Simon Flexner about Landsteiner ( For Mackenzie's planned biography of Landsteiner. Includes a letter to Esther Judkins about Flexner and Landsteiner.) Correspondence (2 items) 1944, 1951 English
Mackenzie, George M. The University of Vienna when Karl Landsteiner was there ( Records on Landsteiner's education in Vienna. See also folders entitled "Background: Vienna, Austria. Karankenhaus, Inst. Path.-Anat.;" "Background material on Austria and Vienna;" "Material about Vienna;" "Vienna faculty of medicine.") Records (65 pages) 1944-1945, n.d. English
Neuburger, Max, 1868-1955 ( Correspondence with George M. Mackenzie regarding Karl Landsteiner.) Correspondence (6 items) 1949-1950 English
Rivers, Thomas M. (Thomas Milton), 1888-1962 ( Notes and recollections of Landsteiner.) Correspondence (3 items) 1944-1952 English
Rockefeller Institute. Annual Departmental Reports ( Annual reports from Landsteiner's laboratory at the Rockefeller Institute.) Records (87 pages) 1923-1943 English
Landsteiner, Karl, 1868-1943; Neuburger, Max, 1868-; Rivers, Thomas M.(Thomas Milton),1888-1962.; Rockefeller Institute.; Antisemitism.; Blood.; Immunology; Medical colleges -- Austria -- Vienna.; Medical sciences.
- Photographs, 14.0 Photograph(s); The photographs described at the item level represent a selection from the Biographical data on Darl Landsteiner. They were seperated from the rest of the collection and placed in the graphics collection.
  - Karl Lansteiner, age five, 1873; 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length formal portrait of Lansteiner, age five.
  - Karl Landsteiner formal portrait with mustache and bow tie., 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 view formal portrait of Lansteiner.
  - Karl Landsteiner formal 3/4 view portrait, 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal bust length portrait of Lansteiner.
  - Karl Landsteiner in Laboratory, 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length profile of Landsteiner sitting at desk in laboratory with beakers.
  - Group portrait, Landsteiner and nine other men., ca. 1906; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 length view group portrait of ten men, standing outside, building in background.
    General note
    Note with this photograph offers names for several of the men pictured; identities not confirmed.
  - Karl Landsteiner with stone building in background., 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 view portrait of Landsteiner in later years.
  - Fanny Hess, Karl Landsteiner's Mother, 1.0 Photograph(s); Bust lenght 3/4 view formal portrait of woman with collar.
  - Leopold Landsteiner (?), Karl Landsteiner's Father, 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal bust length portrait of man with beard.
  - Helene Landsteiner, formal portrait, standing., 1901; 1.0 Photograph(s); Helen Landsteiner standing beside table, formal portrait.
  - Helene Wlasto, April 1897, in Romeo and Juliet, 1897, April; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length formal portrait of Helene Wlasto dressed in costume for play.
  - Helene Wlasto, July 1900, Vienna, 1900, July; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 lenght formal portrait of Helene Wlasto dressed in military attire with sword and cigarette.
  - Karl Landsteiner and Helene Wlasto Landsteiner [?] and another woman, sitting outside at table., ca. 1940; 1.0 Photograph(s); Landsteiner and two women sitting outside, exterior wall of house in background.
  - Karl Landsteiner sitting on ground in Vermont, 1937, August 2; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length candid view of Landsteiner sitting on ground, beside exterior wall of building.
    Note on back of photograph: "K. L., G [?], VT. Aug. 2, 1937."
  - Landsteiner seated in chair outside with hat., 1937, August 30; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full lenght of Landsteiner seated in chair outside.
    Note on back of photograph: " 'Dear doctor, you need a shave?' New Farm, VT. Aug. 30, 1937."